Rishi Sharma Data Scientist

Contact: - +91 8860551924 rishisharma2628@gmail.com

BRIEF

Data science professional with 5+ years of experience in predictive analytics, consulting and data modelling using different supervised and unsupervised methodologies, using python and tensorflow. Versed with handling clients from various geographies and domains to drive better decision-making, provide meaningful insights hidden in data.

SKILLS (CONSULTING)

- Proficient at problem analysis and solving
- Adept at articulating and conveying ideas aptly
- Independent learner with strong team-work ethics
- Competitive attitude and problem solving
- Confident, articulate, professional speaking abilities

SKILLS (TECHNICAL)

- PROGRAMMING: Python, C++, SQL, HTML, Git, Bash
- MACHINE LEARNING: Regression, Random Forest, XGBoost, KMeans Clustering, Neural Networks, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing, Scikit-Learn, Tensorflow, Keras, Pyspark
- DATABASE: Postgres, Apache Hive, Amazon DynamoDB
- VISUALIZATION: Plotly, matplotlib, Seaborn, Tableau
- MLOPS:- Docker, Kubernetes, Kubeflow, AWS, GCP

EXPERIENCE

Data Science Consultant | Deloitte, Gurgaon | February 2021 to Present (2+ Years)

Project 1 - Chabot with Integrated Recommendation System

- Created a voice enabled chatbot on AWS Lex and Poly to take orders from customers in drive through, for a global restaurant chain
- Designing & implementing the flow for the chatbot including providing the utterances for training, creating the intent slots & managing edge cases
- Training a recommendation system to suggest menu items to customers for faster order processing and better user experience
- Using REST APIs to perform CRUD operations utilizing Django, Flask, Postgres and python.

Project 2 - Credit Risk Modelling - Credit Cards

- Preforming Market Segmentation to target specific consumers with higher credit card acceptance, in order to reduce customer acquisition cost
- Analysing data of customers with no credit history, such as rolling average account balance, number of weekly transactions, items purchased, etc
- Creating a probabilistic model to estimate their probability to default & creating decile & lift charts to shortlist the people in top 2 deciles.
- Creating Docker images to be hosted on AWS. Using Kubernetes to manage, scaling and deploying containers.

Data Scientist | Optum (UnitedHealth Group), Gurgaon | February 2019 To February 2021 (2 Years)

Project 1 - Insurance Recommendation Model

- Building Machine Learning models for health care providers to shortlist customers for better sales & lower customer acquisition cost.
- Analysing RX and Medical claims history of members, from hive database along with other related details like Demographics,
 Online activity, AWV and other factors that could aid in the improvement of acceptance rate.
- Creating the Model based on the above user data. Recommendation from model led to 4% volume uplift. Received recognition from client's end.

Project 2 - Insurance - NLP Based Service Navigation

- Making use of machine learning models to perform multi-class classification for the user submitted insurance claims.
- Generating word embeddings using NLP models such as transformers, glove, Word2Vec, GPT and BERT.
- Integrating the model in production pipeline over AWS. Cutting down operational cost by \$ 100K dollars across 3 claim centres.

Associate Software Engineer | Accenture, Gurgaon | September 2017 to February 2019 (1.5 Years)

$Project\ 1-Credit\ Risk\ Modelling-Loan\ Defaults$

- Made use of an ensemble of machine learning models to perform classification on credit defaulters with no loan history.
- Making use of user specific data such as age, income, occupation, collateral, etc. to predict metrics such as PD, LGD and EAD for each user.
- Modelling led to a reduction in default rate by 3% saving a total of potential \$50K for client across 7 bank branches.

EDUCATION

- Maharaja Agrasen Institute of Technology, Delhi B. Tech (Electronics and Communication)
- 2) St Mary's School, Safdarjung Enclave, Delhi
- 1) 12th (PCM + Computer Science)

Aug 2013 – June 2017 (Aggregate Percentage – 74%) Apr 2011 – Mar 2013 (Aggregate Percentage – 91%)